玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋
ln the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence...
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
假如预测到要起狂风
What ifthe forecast predicted high winds...
风速有10倍音速 又将怎样呢？
ten times the speed of sound?
晚上下起倾盆的硫酸雨
An evening downpour of sulfuric acid rain...
或刮起了持续300年 两倍地球大小范围的飓风又当如何呢？
or a hurricane two times the size of Earth lasting 300 years?
这不是科幻素材电影
This is not the stuff of a science fiction movie.
而是来自宇宙的天气预报
These are actual weather reports from around the universe...
是地球天气的极限
and it's Earth's weather to the extreme.
我们来盘点一下宇宙所创造的最大 最糟糕
We are counting down some of the biggest, baddest...
最古怪 最疯狂的天气
weirdest, and wildest weather the universe creates.
请系好你的安全带 开始崎岖之旅
Fasten your seatbelts. lt's going to be a bumpy ride.
这就是宇宙中的凶悍气候
This is "The Universe: Wildest Weather in the Cosmos."
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第十五集 宇宙中的凶悍气候
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 15of18 Wildest.Weather.in.the.Cosmos
天气是大气的状态
Weather is the state of an atmosphere.
我们可能认为 我们作为太阳的第三行星很不理想
We might thinkwe've got it bad on the third planet from the Sun...
有剧烈的雷暴
with vicious thunderstorms...
炎热难当
oppressive heat...
还有温度很低 有时难以忍受
and temperatures so low, they're sometimes unbearable.
但是 这里的天气与宇宙其他地方相比
But weather here is a walk in the park...
只能算小菜一碟
compared to weather elsewhere in the universe.
风雨雷暴呈现出另一番奇怪的含义
Rain, wind, and storms take on a whole new and strange meaning.
虽然 影响这些天气事件的机制
And while the mechanics that power these weather events...
如地球一般高深莫测
are strangely similar to Earth's...
但是 结果却难以想象
the results are terrifying to contemplate.
金星温度有900华氏度
lt's 900 degrees Fahrenheit on Venus...
每天都如烤炉那样
hotter than a pizza oven every day.
火星极其干燥 天寒地冻
Mars is bone-dry and colder than ice-cold.
你看到闪电
You've got lightning...
你看到风暴
you've got storms.
所有这些天气现象最终的成因
All those weather phenomena are ultimately driven...
在于阳光不均匀照射所造成的温差
by the fact that the temperature differences...created by uneven input of sunlight...
引起的大气运动
are going to cause motions in the atmosphere.
或许地球的最终命运的答案
Perhaps the answers to Earth's ultimate fate...
就在这巨大的太空之谜中
lie in the great unknown of space.
我们来拍点一下宇宙所提供的最极端的天气
And we are counting down the most extreme weather...the universe has to offer.
你想了解我们星球的气候可能的转变途径吗？
You want to learn about which way our planet can turn climatically?
那就看一下我们太阳系里的邻近星球吧
Have a look at some neighboring planets...within our own solar system.
科学家知道所有天气都始于一样东西:热
Scientists know all weather starts with one thing: Heat.
热是创造风的媒介
Heat is a catalyst that creates winds.
其它行星上的风
And there are winds on other planets...
完全不同于地球母亲所遇到过的
unlike anything Mother Earth has ever seen.
木星是颗巨大的行星
Jupiter is a monster planet.
如果你将所有的行星加在一起
lfyou add up all the planets together...
还够不上这颗叫做木星的巨大行星
theywould not total the gigantic planet called Jupiter.
木星是行星游乐园
Jupiter is the planetary amusement park...
在提及大风的天气时
when it comes to windy conditions.
木星上的高空气流很酷
Jet streams on Jupiter are pretty cool.
在地球上 大约说来
Here on Earth, we, roughly speaking...
在南北半球各有一条高空气流
have about onejet stream per hemisphere.
木星就不一样了
Jupiter's different.
木星大约有30条高空气流
Jupiter has about thirtyjet streams.
它们都与云带结合在一起
These are associated with the cloud bands.
木星的气流环绕着星球
Jupiter"sjet streams rip around the planet...
反方向行进
running in opposite directions.
通过其表面不同的颜色来界定
Defined by different colors invisible on its surface...
这些气流四处奔忙于
thesejet streams tear around...
木星厚达1000英里的大气层里
Jupiter"s astounding 1,000-mile-thick atmosphere.
地球 相比之下 只有一点点高空气流
Earth, in comparison, has only a fewjet streams...
大气层也只有100英里厚
and an atmosphere only100 miles thick.
但是 为何或有这么多的气流 为何风肆虐这颗星球
But why so manyjet streams, and why winds at all on a planet...
而它得到的阳光甚至只有地球的四分之一
that doesn't even get a quarter ofthe sunlight as Earth?
一种理论认为这些风是
One theory suggests these winds are a direct result...
这颗热行星正在自我冷却的直接结果
ofthis hot planet just trying to cool itself off.
木星是颗大行星 质量超过地球300多倍
Jupiter is a huge planet, over 300 Earth masses.
其形成伴随着大量的热
And it formed with a huge, huge amount of heat.
它个头之大以至于它还在努力摆脱这种生成热
And it's so big that it's still trying to get rid of this heat offormation.
这种持续的热释放缓慢地上升到了木星的大气层里
This constant release of heat slowly rises into Jupiter"s atmosphere...
遭遇到了冷空气
and collides with cooler air.
和地球一样 她需要平衡冷暖气流
Like Earth and her need to balance hot and cold streams of air...
在高低压系统中
in high and low-pressure systems...
木星也在为常态而抗争
Jupiter also struggles for normalcy.
能量带一直以来驱动着木星大气层
That energy band is used to drive the various storms and winds...
上部的风暴和气流
in the upper atmosphere of Jupiter.
木星的气流实在凶猛
Thejet streams on Jupiter are really ferocious.
其时速达到数百英里
They go at several hundred miles per hour...
大量气体压缩在气流中
and there's a lot of gas zipping along this stream.
但是完全不同于地球上相当稳定的气流
But unlike on Earth, thejet streams are pretty stable.
地球上 很少见到地面风有超过时速200英里的
On Earth, it's rare for surface winds...to reach over 200 miles per hour.
木星上的气流的速度
Jet streams on Jupiter reach speeds...
居然高达时速300英里
exceeding up to about 300 miles per hour.
真是太快了 你都迈不出步了
That's really fast. And you can't get out.
你会被困在气流之中
You're trapped inside thejet stream.
穿行木星的赤道气流
Traveling through Jupiter's equatorial jet stream...
就像是驾乘地狱过山车
would be like a roller coaster ride from hell.
就像是这个永不停止 永无尽头的过山车
lt's like this continuous, never-ending roller coaster ride.
我好喜欢啊
l love it!
好刺激啊
What a thrill!
你会被抛上甩下上百英里
You would be pushed up and down by up to a hundred miles.
厉害
- This is huge. - Oh, man.
其引起的压力变化远大于
lt would lead to a much greater change in pressure...
从地面登上珠穆朗玛峰顶
than going from the Earth's surface up to the top of Mount Everest.
木星的气流叹为观止
Jupiter'sjet streams are pretty impressive...
但是 300英里时速与我们下一颗行星相比可谓小巫见大巫了
but 300 miles per hour is nothing compared to our next planet.
乍一看 海王星是最后的地方
At first glance, Neptune is the last place...
科学家预计会发现狂暴的天气 更不用提狂风大作了
scientists expect to find wild weather, let alone vicious winds.
这个冰冷的星球上热并不充分
Heat is not in abundance on this chilly planet.
海王星极度寒冷
Neptune is frigid, frigid cold.
海王星所吸收的阳光只有地球的0.1%
Neptune only absorbs 0.1 percent ofthe sunlight that Earth does.
1989年之前 海王星一直被认为是极其乏味的
Up until 1989, Neptune was considered, well, boring.
远离太阳 拥有一个165年的运行轨道
Sitting far away from the Sun and having an orbit of165 years...
科学家并不认为这颗蓝色星球上会有多少发现
scientists didn't believe much was to be discovered on the blue planet.
航海者2号的造访改变了一切
A visit from Voyager ll changed all that.
在航天器掠过这颗行星时
As the orbiter zoomed past the planet...
科学家被发现的云的踪迹惊呆了
scientists were shocked to discover traces of clouds.
最为惊讶的是 这些云围绕海王星的速度
Most surprising, these clouds were traveling around Neptune...
难以置信
at ferocious speeds.
有东西在裹挟着它们
Something was carrying them.
是风吗 离太阳这么远？
But wind, so far away from the Sun?
海王星是太阳系里风力最大的行星
Neptune is the windiest planet in the solar system.
海王星表面的风超过时速1000英里
Winds blow on the surface of Neptune over1,000 miles per hour.
设想一下 突破了声障
lmagine that, breaking the sound barrier...
你随时一看 风就呼啸而过
every time you simply look up and the winds blow past you.
科学家估计风速高达每小时1500英里
Scientists estimate winds reach up to 1,500 miles per hour...
取决于天气条件和风暴的发展
depending on weather conditions and storms that develop.
我们太阳系里一个重大之谜
A major unsolved puzzle in our solar system...
事实上就是海王星的风速
is the fact that the wind speeds on Neptune...
居然超过了木星的风速
are actually much faster than those on Jupiter...
尽管 事实上 海王星接收的阳光
despite the fact that Neptune receives...
或许只有木星的4%
only maybe four percent of the sunlight that Jupiter does.
这种阳光或热的贫乏
This lack of sunlight or heat...
完全违背了科学家所知道的
completely contradicts what scientists know...
地球上风的形成规律
about howwinds develop here on Earth.
你可能会认为阳光越强
You might think that the stronger the sunlight...
风也会越强
the stronger the winds would be.
在将地球与海王星相提并论时 这显然是不对的
This is obviously not true when comparing Earth to Neptune...
因为 地球上的风通常时速30英里
since Earth's winds are typically maybe thirty miles per hour...
然而 海王星的风速高达每小时900英里
whereas those on Neptune reach 900 miles per hour.
科学家怀疑内部存在热
Scientists suspect there is internal heat left over...
是海王星在几十亿年前形成时残留的
from Neptune's formation billions ofyears ago...
但是 困惑的是 这个内部的热怎么会
but are perplexed how this internal heat...
足够以这样的速度来推动风的呢？
could be enough to drive winds to this speed.
海王星释放的热是太阳投入的两倍
There's twice as much heat getting out of Neptune...as what the Sun is putting in.
可是 这还不足以解释海王星上的巨风
However, that's not enough to explain the tremendous winds of Neptune.
科学已经提出了另一个有关海王星狂风的假设
And science has come up with another hypothesis...for Neptune's racing winds.
缺少摩擦可能会让这些风
A lack offriction might allow these winds...
围绕着星球畅通无阻
to fly uninhibited around the planet.
我们要十分感谢地球存在着摩擦
We can be very thankful that there's friction on Earth.
摩擦来自风击打树木和建筑这样的东西
Friction comes about when the winds...are banging into things like trees and buildings...
以及山峦这样的地形
and terrain like mountains...
所以摩擦最终会减缓风速
so friction ends up slowing down the winds.
和其它气体巨星一样 海王星没有固体表面
Like other gas giants, Neptune has no solid surface.
即使阳光非常微弱
Even though the sunlight is extremelyweak...
只要摩擦也非常微弱
ifthe friction is also extremely weak...
那么你就可以随着时间的推移积累成极快的风速
then you can build up very fast winds over time.
海王星的风是太阳系里最引人注目的
Neptune's winds are the most impressive in our solar system...
但是宇宙可是个大地方啊
but the universe is a big place.
这里的冠军与外太空的天气相比
And what is a champion here pales in comparison...
就相形见绌了
to weatherfurther out in space.
或许行星科学上最激动人心的发现
Perhaps the most exciting discovery in planetary science...
就是最令人乍舌的风 那是我们指望永远不要体验的
are the most amazing winds we could hope to never experience.
如果你想体验宇宙间最狂野的风
lfyou want to experience the wildest winds in the cosmos...
那么热木星就是你的终点了
then hot Jupiters are your destination.
热木星属于日外行星
Hot Jupiters are a class of exoplanets.
它肯定不是你想去的地方
lt's definitely not a place you want to be.
它比海王星要糟糕上好多好多
lt's much, much worse than Neptune.
温度高上好多 风要快上好多
lt's much hotter. The winds are much faster.
所以 你想找块平静之地来开张营业的话
So, ifyou want a nice kind of calm place to set up shop...
你或许会相中海王星
you'd probably be better off going with Neptune.
这些家伙肯定都是糟透了
These guys are definitely much, much worse.
热木星紧紧围绕着自己的母星
Hot Jupiters orbit tightly around their stars...
比水星距离太阳还要近
far closer than Mercury to our own Sun.
以至于酷热导致了某些狂野的天气
And all that intense heat makes for some wild weather.
作为比较 其从母星那里接受的阳光2万倍于
For comparison, it gets about 20,000 times more light...
木星从太阳所接受的阳光
from its star than Jupiter does from the Sun.
这些行星的温度极高
The temperatures on these planets are enormous...
介于1500至2000华氏度之间 甚至更高
between 1,500 and 2,000 degrees Fahrenheit or more.
有些热木星被潮汐锁定
Some hot Jupiters are tidally locked...
引力效应使得它们始终将自己的一面
a gravitational effect that leads them to show the same face...
露给自己的母星
to their star at all times.
你看到这个行星的一面
You've got one side of this planet...
始终受到其母星的阳光的煎熬
that's being just blasted with light from the star all the time.
所以你可以料到那里非常非常的热
So you would expect that to be very, very hot.
然而 同时 你可以看到这颗行星的阴影面
But at the same time, you've got this night side ofthe planet...
从不见母星的丝毫阳光
that never sees any light from the star.
所以 要知道 或许那阴影面其实是非常寒冷的
So, you know, perhaps that night side is actually quite cold.
为获得热木星的温度
Taking hot Jupiters' temperatures...
科学家测量了行星在经过其前面遮挡
scientists measured how much light is eclipsed from the planet...
以及在其背后所产生的光
as it passes in front of and behind its star during its orbit.
它们实际上在红外光波上相对强一些
So they actually glow relatively brightly at infrared wavelength.
因此 你想获得行星的温度
So ifyou want to take the temperature of a planet...
你就要获得这些红外波长
you want to look at these infrared wavelengths.
你要测量它们发出的热
You want to measure the heat that they're giving off.
但是 日照面与阴影面之间的温差
But the temperature difference...between the day side and night side...
实际上没什么差异
is virtually the same.
就极端状况而言 这是不可思议的
This was astounding, considering the extreme situation.
有东西在将热从日照面传递到阴影面
Something was transferring the heat...from the day side to the night side.
那是什么呢？
But what?
惊人的风速就是答案
Winds traveling at amazing speeds were the answer.
因此 我们的模型告诉我们
And so our models tell us...
风速有可能达到每小时6000英里
that the winds could be as fast as maybe 6,000 miles per hour.
推测某些热木星上有时速6000英里的风速
The 6,000-mile-per-hourwinds inferred on some hot Jupiters...
远超过我们太阳系里已知的所有风速
is much faster than any winds that we know of in our solar system.
时速6000英里有多快？
Howfast is 6,000 miles per hour?
以那样的速度 你可以在20分钟里
At that speed, you could travel...
从纽约抵达洛杉矶
fom NewYork to Los Angeles in twenty minutes.
你看到了温度高得惊人的日照面
You've got this incredibly hot day side.
你看到所有高温气体产生于日照面
And so you've got all this hot gas sitting there on the day side...
好像它应该会快速地流向阴影面
and sort ofwhat it wants to do...is to kind of go rushing around to the night side.
热气体产生的风
Winds are created by hot air...
应该会流向行星的阴影面
wanting to travel to the cold side of the planet.
所以说有点像冲浪风帆
So it's a little bit like a windsurfer.
如果你来这里碰上刮风天 竖起风帆
lfyou come out here on a windy day and you put your sail up...
就可以赶上理想的风
you can really catch a good breeze...
就可以在港口驰骋了
and you can go flying across the harbor.
那些行星的状况也一样
lt's the same thing with these planets.
你遇上惊人的强风
You have such incredibly strong winds...
它们搭上气体的便车
that they can really just pick that gas up...
一路横扫到阴影面
and whip it all the way around to the night side...
直到整个冷却下来
before it even cools off at all.
很难驾驭那样的天气的
lt's hard to beat weather like that.
时速6000英里的风
Six thousand-mile-an-hourwinds...
你碰上这样的行星会如痴如醉的
is about as crazy as you can get with a planet.
在提及太空中的天气时
Scientists have learned to expect the unexpected...
科学家已感到出乎意料
when it comes to weather in space.
有时风会变成龙卷风那样的风暴
Sometimes winds become storms like tornadoes.
星际龙卷风变幻莫测
And galactic tornadoes are unpredictable...
其行动相当诡异
and behave in ratherweird ways.
最近一个规模宏大的龙卷风在太空中发现了
Recently, a tornado of epic proportions was discovered in space.
这个太空龙卷风就是赫比格 - 哈罗天体
This space tornado is a Herbig-Haro object...
是一颗正在形成的恒星产生的风创造出来
created by winds as the result of a forming star.
赫比格 - 哈罗天体是一个发光的气体云
A Herbig-Haro object is a glowing cloud of gas...
是高速喷射的气体
produced when a high-speed jet of gas...
猛击周围静止的气体时生成的
smashes into surrounding, essentially, stationary gas.
这个高速射流加热静止的气体
So this high-speed jet heats the stationary gas...
使其发光
and causes it to glow.
这个天体不费吹灰之力就坐上了
This object would easily be number one...
宇宙间最猛烈龙卷风的头把交椅
on the list ofwildest tornadoes in the universe...
出了一个重要的事实
except for one important fact.
它其实不是龙卷风
lt's not actually a tornado.
其形状与龙卷风并无二异
lts shape is very suggestive of a tornado.
它具有螺旋状
lt has this helical shape to it...
看上去一路盘旋
that looks like it is twisting along...
但是它其实并不是龙卷风那样的旋转物体
but it's actually not a rotating object like a tornado.
并不像地球上的龙卷风那样
Unlike a tornado on Earth...
旋风创造出一个漏斗状
where a vortex ofwind creates a conical shape...
这个由磁力产生的龙卷风
this tornado is created by magnetic forces...
正在创作宇宙尘埃粒子的尾流
creating a wake of cosmic dust and particles.
这东西里面好像呈现出螺旋状
This one appears to have sort of a spiral shape within it.
那确实有点怪异 因为其它大多数
And that's really kind ofweird because most of the others...
确实没有螺旋状
really don't have the spiral pattern.
不过旋转的原因或许有别于地球上的龙卷风
But the cause of the spin is probably different...from that of a tornado on Earth.
星际龙卷风的亚军
Number two on the galactic tornado list...
更像我们在地球上所看到的龙卷风
is much more like tornadoes we find at home...
它高高地矗立着
and it's a towering presence.
它们被称为尘暴
They're called dust devils...
它们是火星对星际龙卷风的回应
and they are Mars' answer to a planetary tornado.
火星上的尘暴很酷
Dust storms on Mars are pretty cool.
每个火星年都会发生数千个风暴
There are thousands of local storms that occur every Mars year...
引发了昏暗的尘埃云
meaning dust clouds that are opaque...
或许会穿越数十乃至数百英里
and maybe tens to hundreds of miles across...
会有几英里高
and a few miles tall.
通常一说起红色星球
Often referred to as the Red Planet...
火星就是个尘土飞扬的荒漠之地
Mars is a dusty and dismal place.
其表面覆盖着沙层
lts surface is covered by sand.
很显然 其表面没有液态水
Apparently, there is no liquid water on the surface.
在这个尘土飞扬的地区 太阳一旦升起 麻烦也就开始了
And in this dusty terrain, when the Sun rises, trouble starts.
尘暴可以宽达数百码
Dust devils can be hundreds ofyards wide...
半英里甚至更高
and half a mile or more tall...
以时速70英里盘旋扫过地表
spinning seventy miles an hour across the surface...
它们可是地球龙卷风的同类
and they have similarities to Earth's own tornadoes.
至于尘暴里的基本力量
As far as the basic forces inside a dust devil...
非常类似于龙卷风里的
they're pretty similar to in a tornado.
两者都是在细长的漩涡里 在低压中心
They're both thin vortices that rotate and are low-pressure centers.
然而 龙卷风要强烈得多得多
Yet a tornado is much, much stronger...
往往达到风速的数量级
often by an order of magnitude in wind speed.
龙卷风的能量是毋庸置疑的
The power of a tornado is undeniable.
爱荷华州立大学的科学家
And scientists at lowa State University...
似乎没法充分获得过这些暴风
can't seem to get enough of these violent storms.
他们在这里建造了世界上最大的龙卷风模拟器
Here they have built the largest tornado simulator in the world...
来了解漩涡的形成
to understand vortex formation.
了解小尺度龙卷风的能量
Understanding the power of a tornado on a small scale here...
有可能让科学家了解哪些更大尺度
might lead scientists to understand these beasts...
甚至星系尺度上的龙卷风
on a grander or even galactic scale.
科学家利用干冰和包装的花生
Scientists use dry ice and packing peanuts...
来观察漩涡的情形
to observe vortex behavior.
上方有个6英尺直径的风扇 如你所见
We have a six-foot-diameterfan on top of me, as you can see...
它可以产生吸力
which produces the suction.
气流上升 穿过外面的管道
And the flow goes up and comes through the outer duct...
旋转起来
and it's rotating.
然后气流集中到中心
And then the flow converges to the center...
再次升起 在其升起时
and again goes up. And as it's going up...
会形成一定规模的旋风 是我们能够控制的
it produces the vortex of a certain size, which we can control.
这些因素结合起来可以理想地模拟
Combined, these elements perfectly mimic...
旋风的形成
the formation of a vortex...
随着它的增强 从底部形成了一个漏斗
as it swells from its base and grows to a funnel.
科学家了解到 和地球上的龙卷风一样
Scientists know that, just like tornadoes on Earth...
尘暴是从地面往上形成的
dust devils form from the ground up.
阳光照射 加热地面
Sunlight comes down and heats up the surface...
而热量需要通过热气团来对流
and that heat needs to be convected away...by hot blobs of air.
热气团从地面离开后 空气会被吸进去
As these hot blobs move away from the surface, air is drawn in.
就像滑冰者收拢自己的手臂一样
And just like an ice skater pulling in her arms...
空气旋转会越来越快
that air spins up, moving faster and faster...
在高速带动下
and with those higher speeds...
会将尘埃卷入大气层
kicks dust up into the atmosphere.
随着热气团在地表的移动
As this hot blob of air moves away from the surface...
尘暴会升高 变得更强
the dust devil will become taller and stronger...
直到数百米甚至更高
reaching altitudes of several hundred meters or more...
宽度通常有数百米
and widths of typically a hundred meters...
会变得更强
and will get stronger...
尘埃会源源不断流入其中
as dust continues to be injected into its interior.
然后 尘暴会消失在远方
And then, the dust devil will move off into the distance.
然而 一旦未来的火星殖民者
However, if a future space colonist...
被困在尘暴中
was trapped in a Mars dust devil...
是不会危及生命的
it wouldn't be fatal.
火星上的大气非常稀薄
The atmosphere on Mars is very thin...
所以风吹到你身上 也几乎觉察不到
so the wind could be blowing on you, and you'd barely feel it.
你身上的气压相对较低
The pressure on you would be relatively low...
所以你不会嚷嚷 "噢 怎么回事
so you're not going to say, "Oh, what was that?
"我居然被尘暴击倒了"
"l just got bowled over by a dust devil."
那种情况是不会发生的
That's not going to happen.
最后盘点的星际龙卷风事件是个真正的谜团
The final galactic tornado event on the countdown is a true mystery.
原来龙卷风形成背后的理论颠倒了
And it turns theories behind tornado formation upside down.
最后盘点的龙卷风是个双重麻烦
The final tornado on the countdown is double trouble.
金星 曾经被视为浪漫之星
Venus, once viewed as a romantic planet...
有着非常可怕的天气情况
has some truly horrific weather conditions.
温室效应肆虐带来的闷热
Oppressive heat with a greenhouse effect gone amok...
这颗行星在不断设法自我冷却
this is one planet that is constantly trying to cool itself off...
没有得逞
with no success.
金星是个迷人的不友好之地
Venus is a fascinatingly hostile place.
它非常不友好 以至于即使我们把机器送上去
lt's so hostile that even our machines that we send there...
工作上几分钟 零件就会融化掉了
they work for, like, a few minutes, and then the components melt.
由于持续的高温 风暴始终存在于金星上
As a result ofthis constant heat, storms are always present on Venus...
这就产生了一个从未见过的最有趣的漩涡
and this makes for one ofthe most interesting vortex events ever observed.
一对巨大的 上下颠倒的龙卷风
There's a giant, upside down, twin tornado...
固定不变地存在于金星的极地
permanently existing at the pole ofVenus.
自金星快车探测器发回了壮丽的金星图像以来
Ever since the Venus Express Orbiter sent back...magnificent images of Venus...
科学家一直致力于了解颠倒运行于
scientists have struggled to understand the twin vortexes...
其南极地区的孪生漩涡
running upside down at her south polar region.
某种意义上 它是个颠倒的龙卷风
ln a sense, it's an upside down tornado...
因为空气是从漩涡的顶部漏向地面
because the air is funneling from the top part of that spiral...down towards the ground...
而地球上典型的龙卷风
whereas a typical tornado on Earth...
你会看到是通过漏斗往上升的
you think of the air kind of rising up through the funnel.
奇怪的是那是个双龙卷风
And the strange thing is that it's a double vortex.
也就是 反映出两个巨大的龙卷风
That is, picture two giant tornadoes...
好像是互相缠绕着
sort of rotating around each other.
你可以看到两个波瓣 它分成了两半
And you can see the two lobes, the two halves of it here.
科学家认为漩涡是大气中热传导导致的
Scientists believe the vortexes...are a result of heat transfer in the atmosphere.
热从金星的赤道升起
Heat rises atVenus' equator...
然后下沉到星球最冷的地方
then sinks at the coolest section of the planet.
宛如浴缸放水 其中的水…
Like a bathtub draining, where the water is...
水流集中排放 就会形成旋转
That flow is concentrated on the drain...and it leads to this spinning motion.
为何它会是双龙卷风 我们确实无法理解
Why it's a double vortex, we don't really understand that.
它始终是个谜
lt's still mysterious.
这个风暴在火星上很庞大
This storm is an enormous presence on Venus.
有数千英里宽
lt's thousands of miles across.
其产生的风达到了时速数百英里
The winds it generates are hundreds of miles an hour...
这些漩涡是金星上的固定标志
and these vortexes are a permanent fixture on Venus.
太空中的天气千奇百怪
Weather takes many strange forms in space...
包括下雨
even rain.
不过其他行星的大气层
But other planets have atmospheres...
是由不同的化学成分构成的
made up of different chemicals.
话说回来 降雨的成分
ln turn, rain is formed...
对人类将会是致命的
from ingredients that would be lethal to humans.
这些有毒降雨
And these toxic rains...
是你在太空中所见到的最糟糕的
are some of the worst you'll find anywhere in space.
远远经过土星之环
Far out past the rings of Saturn...
有一颗太阳系里第二大的卫星
lies the second biggest moon in the solar system...
土卫六
Titan.
2005年 卡西尼-惠更斯探测器穿越土卫六的大气层
ln 2005, the Huygens-Cassini probe pierced Titan's atmosphere...
登陆其表面
landing on its surface.
发现那是个地貌与地球极为相似的地方
What it discovered was a place with features eerily similar to Earth's.
土卫六是太阳系里唯一一个行星体
Titan is the only planetary body in the solar system...
具有类似地球的海洋
that has seas like Earth.
事实上 我把土卫六看作是疯狂版的地球
ln fact, l regard Titan as a deranged version of Earth.
科学家兴奋地发现有山有水
Scientists were excited to discover mountains, washes...
甚至苏必利尔湖大小的湖泊
even lakes the size of Lake Superior.
土卫六 江河湖海中的液体不是水
And the liquid that fills Titan's lakes and rivers isn't water.
而是甲烷
lt's methane.
我可不想去那些湖里游泳
l wouldn't want to go swimming in one ofthose lakes.
那是液态甲烷 极其寒冷
They're liquid methane, which is extraordinarily cold.
那就意味着一旦冷凝发生在这个星球上
And that means when condensation occurs on this planet...
就会降下甲烷
it rains methane.
土卫六的降雨不是每天都会发生的
Rain on Titan isn't an everyday occurrence.
事实上 科学家也只看到了没几次云的形成
ln fact, scientists have only witnessed cloud formation a few times.
但是 证据比比皆是
But the evidence is everywhere...
深度冲刷是大范围降雨的结果
deep washes as a result of significant rainfall.
这里是图森
Here we are in Tucson.
这里好多天没下雨了 通常不下雨
lt hasn't rained for days, and it doesn't usually rain...
但是偶尔会下很大的雨
but, occasionally, it rains very strong...
我们可以看到有大量的水冲刷这里
and we get a lot ofwater coming through this wash...
侵蚀这堵墙
and eroding this wall.
我们在土卫六看到同样的证据
This is the same kind of evidence we see on Titan...
那里通常不下雨
where usually it doesn't rain...
但是 偶尔 会造成惊人的冲刷
but, occasionally, it produces phenomenal washes.
土卫六的暴雨可能非常厉害
Rainstorms on Titan might be pretty violent.
我们看到地表有大量的侵蚀痕迹
We see lots of erosional patterns on the surface...
那表明一些暴雨是相当的强劲
that suggest that some of these storms...have been pretty powerful.
科学家认为土卫六上的风暴的发展需要时间
Scientists believe it takes time for a storm to develop on Titan.
偶尔 大量的云会堆积起来形成暴雨
And every once in a while, enough clouds build so a rainstorm occurs.
那么我们真看到风暴又会如何呢？
So what ifwe do see a storm here?
会是什么样子的呢？
What would it look like?
大到不可思议
Well, the big ones are incredible.
它们会覆盖整个天空 从这头到那一头
Theywould cover the sky from one end to the next...
我们会看到和风细雨从天而降
and we would eventually start seeing these very gently falling drops...
要比我们在地球上看到的缓和多了
much slower than the rain that we have on Earth.
事实上 整个看上去似乎是慢动作
ln fact, everything would seem to be in slow motion.
风会比较柔和
The winds would be a little bit slower...
雨滴缓缓落下 那可不是水
and the drops would gently land, and theywouldn't be water.
它们可是天然气
They would be natural gas.
想象一下 有毒的黏稠原油细雨
lmagine a toxic drizzle with the consistency ofwaxy crude oil...
一直是零下300度
all at minus 300 degrees.
那就是土卫六
That's Titan.
回到金星上 从来就不存在问题
Back on Venus, there's never an issue...
因为太阳提供着足够的热量
with getting enough heat from the Sun.
由于 二氧化碳永远被困在大气层里
With carbon dioxide forever trapped in the atmosphere...
其温室效应已经失控了
it has a greenhouse effect gone wild.
已经到了热产生了冷凝云
All that heat creates condensation and clouds...
充满了硫酸
thick with sulfuric acid.
真是个讽刺
Here's the irony.
金星是以美的女神命名的
Venus is named for the goddess of beauty.
美丽金星的源头居然是科学上最出名的酸之一
The source of the beauty ofVenus...is one of the most potent acids known to science.
换句话说 女性并不是来自金星
ln otherwords, women are not from Venus.
那里好像风暴和对流一刻不停
There seem to be storms and convection patterns that move around.
云层里到处都是一片动荡
There are places within those clouds...that are very turbulent.
金星的暴雨发生在离地30英里处
Rainstorms on Venus happen thirty miles up from the surface...
云层底部 持续下着酸雨
in the cloud beds, and acid rain falls constantly.
金星的酸雨实际上确确实实是电池酸液
The thing about the acid rain on Venus...is that it literally is battery acid.
非常强 那酸会腐蚀皮肤 危害极大
lt's so strong, that acid...that it would eat through skin and do very nasty things.
所以 不管你身体的什么部位
So whatever's left ofyour body...
都会被硫酸烧成灰烬
would be burnt into a charred piece of powder...by the sulfuric acid.
然而最后盘点的雨
But the final rain on the countdown...
是最最有毒的 或许就是最危险的
is the most toxic, if not the most dangerous of all.
宇宙间 失败的恒星 即所谓的褐矮星
Throughout the universe, failed stars, called brown dwarfs...
隐藏在暗处
hide in the shadows.
虽然它们比我们最大的行星木星大多了
While they're more massive than our largest planet, Jupiter...
但是它们太昏暗了 望远镜都很难发现
they are so faint, telescopes have trouble detecting them.
褐矮星是失败之星
A brown dwarf is a failed star.
它是自残者
lt's a wannabe.
它是一个从未完全形成的气球
lt's a ball of gas that never quite made it.
你要有一定量的气体
You have to have a certain amount of gas...
然后才能燃烧 才能出现一个美丽的恒星
before you get ignition and you get a beautiful star emerging.
褐矮星就没有做到
A brown dwarf just didn't make it.
尽管 没有成功成为恒星
Despite being a failure as a star...
但是 褐矮星的温度依然相当可观
temperatures on brown dwarfs are still pretty impressive...
达到了3000华氏度
at over 3,000 degrees Fahrenheit.
不同于恒星会热到产生天气
And unlike stars that are too hot to have weather...
褐矮星会冷到足以经历对流和冷凝
brown dwarfs have cooled enough...to experience convection and condensation.
在那样的温度下
At these temperatures...
降雨具有全新的可怕含义
rain takes on a whole new terrifying meaning.
褐矮星的大气层深处
Deep in the atmosphere of a brown dwarf...
温度高到铁都成了蒸汽了
it's so hot that even iron is a vapor.
那种气就像是地球大气层里的水
lt's a gas like water is in our own atmosphere.
铁蒸汽上升 冷却凝固 变成了沙子
As iron vapors rise up, they cool, solidify, and turn to sand.
铁会凝结起来
The iron would start to condense...
你就看到了云 大团的云
and you have clouds, big, puffy clouds...
只是这云是沙粒 滚烫 温度达到1500度
except the clouds would be sand, boiling hot, 1,500 degrees.
因为在褐矮星上
Because in a brown dwarf...
你可以看到木星般大小的东西
you have something the size of Jupiter...
然而 却囊括了木星30 40 甚至50倍的质量
but you've packed in 30 or40 or 50 times the mass of Jupiter...
所以引力非常强
the gravity is very high.
其引力是地球的300倍
lt could be as high as 300 times the gravitywe have on Earth...
因此 物体的坠落要快得多
and so things can fall a lot faster.
喷砂机的高速运动
The highest moving velocity of a sandblaster...
对于褐矮星上的沙粒来说一点都不为过
makes it a pretty good analogy for sand in a brown dwarf.
在褐矮星的大气层里
ln the atmosphere of a brown dwarf...
引力是地球的300倍
the gravity is 300 times what it is here on Earth...
云层里的小沙粒会以时速70 80甚至100英里落下
and these little sand grains in the cloud would be falling...at 70, 80, or100 miles an hour.
非常像喷砂机喷出的沙子
lt would be a lot like the sand coming out of this sandblaster.
这块不锈钢板被喷砂机的力道给扭曲了
This sheet of stainless steel has been warped...by the force of the sandblaster.
你可以想象褐矮星大气层里的铁雨
You can imagine the iron rain in the atmosphere of a brown dwarf...
以每小时上百英里降下
coming down at a hundred miles an hour...
其结果就像这块钢板
what it might do to a sheet like this.
这些液态铁雨滴
These drops of liquid iron...
可能会有2800度 甚至3000华氏度
they may be 2,800, almost 3,000 degrees Fahrenheit...
这些雨滴实际上落下的速度很高
these drops can really start falling at high velocity...
时速50 80 甚至上百英里
fifty, eighty, a hundred miles an hour.
所以你可以想象出你的雨伞会
So you can imagine your umbrella would be torn to shreds...
被这融化的铁冰雹砸得粉碎
by this hail of molten iron.
那将会是炼狱里的暴风雨
lt would be a real rainstorm from hell.
这成了宇宙中最糟糕的天气
This has got to be the worst weather in the universe.
热 对流 冷凝 - 天气要素
Heat, convection, condensation... the elements ofweather.
随便哪个 都会造成其它星球上的豪雨
Alone, they cause spectacular rains...
狂风和热浪
supersonic winds, and heat on other planets.
它们结合在一起 就会形成难以想象的风暴
Combine them, and incredible storms are formed.
风暴需要温差
A storm needs a temperature difference.
在地球上 每个风暴都是太阳不均匀加热导致的
On Earth, every storm is a result of uneven heating by the Sun.
最简单的例子就是海洋要比陆地来的冷
The easiest example is the ocean is colder than the land.
飓风 龙卷风 旋风
Hurricanes, cyclones, and vortexes...
是地球上天气的集大成者
are the great wonders ofweather on Earth...
太空中也一样
but also in space.
不同于地球上的风暴持续几小时或几天
And unlike Earth, where storms last hours or perhaps a few days...
太空中的某些风暴可以持续数百年
some storms in space can last centuries.
那些飓风将使我们地球上的飓风
These hurricanes would make our hurricanes on Earth...
看上去就像是夏季的习习凉风
look like a summer breeze.
海王星具有太阳系里最快的风
Neptune has the fastest winds in the solar system.
然而 它也具有一个大暗斑
But it also has a Great Dark Spot...
一个神秘的飓风般的风暴
a mysterious hurricane-like storm...
出没无常
that appears and disappears with no warning.
它围绕星球逆时针旋转
lt flies around the planet counterclockwise.
旅行者2号发现
Discovered byVoyager ll...
它庞大 表现为黑色
it's big with black and blue features.
其强烈的风暴如地球般大小
lt appears to be a fierce storm about the size of Earth.
科学家尚不清楚其形成的原因
Scientists don't know what causes it to form...
或为何它是黑色的
orwhy it is black.
它如太阳系里另一个风暴那样神秘
lt's a mystery...like another storm in our solar system.
土星以其壮观的光环闻名遐迩
Saturn is famous for its magnificent rings...
但是提起它的大气层就有那么一点神秘了
but is a little mysterious when it comes to its atmosphere.
然而坐等30年
But sit back and wait thirty years...
土星就会出现一个异常壮观的风暴
and Saturn will put on a storm so magnificent...
会给其母亲星球留下深刻的印记
it would impress Mother Nature herself.
它称为大白斑
lt's called the Great White Spot...
每30年就在土星表面形成的巨大风暴
a gigantic storm that develops every thirty years on Saturn's surface...
最终覆盖整个赤道地区
eventually covering the entire equator.
这真是个行星级的现象
lt is truly a planetary-scale phenomenon...
我们认为这是个极其可怕的雷暴
and we think it's a monstrous, monstrous thunderstorm.
科学家观察到了在土星赤道发展的风暴
Scientists have observed the storm developing at Saturn's equator...
那里接收到大部分太阳发出的热量
where it receives the most heat from the Sun.
也许热量随着时间推移聚集起来
Perhaps, heat builds over time...
最终在星球上爆发成风暴
and finally bursts into a storm on a planet...
那里没有地表和摩擦使其速度降下来
that has no surface orfriction to slow it down.
也就是说 就好像是恶性循环
ln otherwords, it's sort of like a vicious circle...
就好像 一旦你将球滚起来 一路滚下山
where, once you get the ball rolling, itjust rolls down the hill...
风暴席卷全球
and, you know, the storm goes global.
几个月后 风暴的能量耗尽
Months later, the storm runs out of energy...
只得再潜伏30年
only to lie dormant for another thirty years.
原因及时间尺度意味着什么
What the cause or time scale means...
科学家确实不清楚
scientists truly don't know.
但是 土星的大白斑并不如我们太阳系里
But Saturn's Great White Spot is not as powerful or everlasting...
最大的风暴那样强大和永恒
as our biggest storm in the solar system.
木星一直是科学遐想的源泉
Jupiter has long been a source offascination for scientists...
只要研究起太空中的狂野天气
when studying wild weather in space...
其大风暴数百年来一直是大饱眼福的景色
and its great storm has been a feast for the eyes for centuries.
木星是太阳系里的巨人
Jupiter is the giant of our solar system...
让其他行星都相形见绌
dwarfing all other planets...
因此 唯一与之适应的天气也成为了
so it's only fitting its weather also becomes a showpiece...
强大的力量和惊人的规模的典范
of sheer force and incredible size.
1664年 天文学家罗伯特·胡克
ln 1664, the astronomer Robert Hooke...
注意到了木星的一些怪异之处
noticed something strange about Jupiter.
那里有个疙瘩 现在我们将其称为大红斑
There was a pimple there, which we now call the Great Red Spot.
它一直固定不变
lt's been stable.
想想看 一个数倍于地球的星际风暴
Think of it, a planetary storm several times the size of the Earth...
1664年以来没什么变化
stable since 1664.
这是我们太阳系惊人的特征之一
This is one of the amazing features of our solar system.
大红斑点的命名之后很久我们才知道那是什么
The Great Red Spot was named that...long before we knew what it was...
因为 你已经可以从地球上的望远镜看到它了
because you can see it from a telescope on Earth.
因此数百年来
And so for hundreds ofyears...
人们已经了解了这个大红斑了
people have known about this Great Red Spot.
大红斑是太阳系里最引人注目的风暴
The Great Red Spot...is the most impressive storm of our solar system...
至少 在300年里一直在扰动
and it's been churning for at least 300 years.
我们太阳系里所有飓风的大妈
The mother of all hurricanes in our solar system...
其实实在木星上
is actually on Jupiter.
严格说它并非飓风
lt's not technically a hurricane...
然而 其行为举止非常像飓风
but it behaves very much like one.
它具有热源 具有旋转的风
lt has a heat source, it has swirling winds...
它让我们地球上的一切都相形见绌
and it dwarfs anything on our planet.
这个风暴非常巨大 你可以将两个地球
This storm is so big, you could take two Earths...
塞进这个风暴的里头
and stick them right inside of the storm.
狂风肆作 时速达300英里
The winds are blowing at 300 miles an hour.
飓风和大红斑都是巨大的漩涡
Both hurricanes and the Great Red Spot are giant vortices.
对于飓风来说 它们是低压中心
ln the case of hurricanes, they're a low-pressure center.
而大红斑则是高压中心
The Great Red Spot is a high-pressure center.
两者 都有高速风盘旋在漩涡中
ln both cases, there are high-speed winds circling the vortex.
像一个大眼睛 风暴始终围绕着木星
Like a giant eye, the storm continuously circles Jupiter.
风速达到时速400英里
Wind speeds reach 400 miles per hour...
大红斑从不显出会减小其强度
and the giant red spot never seems to dwindle in strength.
动力来自木星内部的热量
Powered by the internal heat of Jupiter...
它还吞噬着挡道的一切
it also eats anything in its path.
如果你是个小漩涡
lfyou're a small vortex...
处在大红斑的路径上 你要小心了
and you're in the path of the Great Red Spot, look out.
你将会像小鱼那样被吃掉
You're going to be gobbled up like a little fish.
科学家认为木星缺少地表和摩擦
Scientists believe the lack offriction or surface on Jupiter...
有可能让这个风暴在未来数百年间扰动不停
might allow this storm to churn uninterrupted for centuries more.
在地球上 因为飓风打击大地时伴随很强的摩擦
On Earth, because of the strong friction...
短短几天就会解体
when hurricanes hit land...they tend to fall apart in just a few days.
另一方面 大红斑的寿命会超过百年
On the other hand, the Great Red Spot...has a lifetime of over a hundred years.
我们确实不明白其中的细节
We don't really understand this in detail...
但是 有可能这意味着木星大气层里的摩擦
but it probably it means that the friction...in Jupiter's atmosphere
相对地球的大气层 非常的弱
is very weak...compared to in Earth's atmosphere.
木星是行星的一个很好的例子 即行星本身
Jupiter is a good example of a planet where the planet itself...
至少能提供部分能量
is what's supplying at least some of the energy...
来驾驭风暴持续数百年
to drive a storm that's lasting for centuries.
天气… 大气的状态
Weather...the state of an atmosphere.
纵贯宇宙
Throughout the universe...
类似地球上的天气事件在其他行星上精彩上演
familiarweather events on Earth are played out...in fantastic ways on other planets.
那么 为何要研究其他行星上的天气呢？
But why study weather on other planets at all?
假如你只是就地球研究地球的话
lfyou only ever study Earth...for examples to understand Earth...
你就可能错失这些现象更为广泛的背景
you may be missing a much broader context...in which the phenomenon...
那是你描述所无法割裂的
that you're trying to describe is imbedded.
比如 我们观察地球
So, for example, we look at Earth...
我们讨论温室效应
and we talk about a greenhouse effect.
你要认识它 就必须去瞧一瞧
You want to learn about it, go check it out.
观察金星
Look atVenus.
一厢情愿地认为你解决地球上问题的所有办法
The urge is to believe that all your solutions...
只能通过观察地球来得到
to your problems on Earth can be found by only looking at Earth.
那是短视的 近乎痴人说梦
That is shortsighted, bordering on delusional.
我们在研究陌生的环境中熟悉的过程时
When we study familiar processes in unfamiliar settings...
那真是在考验我们是否明白发生了什么
it really tests whether or not we understand what's happening.
对于其他行星上生命存在的可能性
ln terms of the possibility of life on other planets...
了解其天气状况绝对是关键所在
understanding the weather patterns is absolutely key.
我们是众多行星中的一个
We're one planet of many.
太阳是众多恒星中的一个
The Sun is one star of many.
我们处在星系极其普通的部分
We're in an undistinguished part of the galaxy.
有许多需要通过探索别人的意见来加以认识
There's much to be learned by exploring what others say.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing